[SPEAKER_00]: So then, what is the purpose, your rules, your precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you practice renunciation?
[SPEAKER_01]: The purpose of it is developing the strength of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the absolutely first step for that is to be able to say no to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: To say no to your desires, whims, habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, every
[SPEAKER_01]: All of the main rules upon which a practice is based is they're very practical, so to speak, functional, necessary in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not held because of a belief or because of the authority.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're held because they hold in themselves the practice of meditation and development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, think of the rules as a fertile ground where you can plant seeds of a plant or some trees.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not a tree, it's not a seed, but having a grown tree would be impossible if you don't have a fertile ground to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you see the necessity of the fertile ground, you see the necessity of the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without them, there's no point if you're cultivating seeds and watering the plant, when you have destroyed the fertility of the ground, when you have compromised the fundamental rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what are you trying to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you trying to grow?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're trying to grow the freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is bound by the desire, by the craving, by the feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind is liable to feelings, which means when suffering arises, you won't be able to prevent it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When pleasure arises, you won't be able but to indulge it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you're controlled by what you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're controlled because the mind is too weak in regard to what it feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to become stronger than all those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first step to developing of that strength is mere restraint, being able to say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to everything, forever,
[SPEAKER_01]: But to certain things that are inseparable from desire, craving, ill-will, hate, anything unwholesome, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eating at a certain time of the day... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eating at a certain time, it's again, it's just like, you eat because it is necessary for the body to remain alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you don't want to be using it as a sensuality, as a form of escape, and then you just keep eating throughout the day, eating only what you like, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize a degree of necessity to eat, and that's what you focus on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, if you eat enough calories once in a day, that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is absolutely no reason to eat more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eating more than what you need is going to bound to, is going to be bound to come out of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of craving, out of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not a life-threatening hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, in the evening, you have desire to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: And instead of habitually just giving in to desire and satisfying it by any means, you force yourself to reflect on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know you won't eat, you won't break the rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as a form of restraint, what's the alternative?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's to think, okay, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I pulled by this desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is this hunger controlling my mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you... that's how you go beyond the desire, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I ate a meal at night, I started eating, then I'll be free from desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be free from hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the hunger was not your desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there would have been no desire without the hunger, but the hunger is not a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire is always mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the hunger, when the physical state affects, controls your mind, then it becomes a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you might go and remove the physical state, but the liability of your mind to be controlled by the physical states remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, next physical thing comes, and you're gonna equally be bound by the same desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, you don't set... you can't satisfy a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be chasing and engaging in all sorts of sensuality, you can never satisfy a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not there where you're trying to satisfy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're satisfying physical circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those are not what the desire is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, desire is inseparable from those, but it's not those.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your precepts don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the precepts are basically just like laying out the ground where you can practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just putting up a fence, fertilizing the ground and agreeing upon those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a starting point, you have to start somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all the precepts were basically... That's what I mean, they were quite functional, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, you eat...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning, the monks were allowed to eat in the evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was not specified to eat only in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01]: They could eat many times a day.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, it was sort of becoming impractical for various reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going out at night to collect the food, getting all sorts of accidents and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then it was sort of, a rule was brought in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You eat it, you eat it at the right time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't go out to collect food at night, you go during the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, they could still eat at night, but then you stop eating at night as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just eat when you go and get the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just becomes more practical, easier.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't spend the rest of your day being concerned and planning about the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: You spend it practicing restraint and practicing wisdom and practicing meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like precepts against alcohol.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, those, yeah, the eight precepts, those are the basis of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are the... that's what defines their fertile ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how can you possibly be practicing the clarity of the mind, developing the strength of your mind, when you're drinking alcohol that's clearly, directly affecting the clarity of the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it has no practical value.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you need to eat some food.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to meet a certain degree of... certain amount of calories.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't need to drink alcohol.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's always going to be central reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even people say, oh, I drink only because people around me pressure me to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also a sensual reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're basically afraid of affecting adversely the sensual environment around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to upset anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to have to have to be kind of ostracized or whatever by your friends or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to develop the strength of your mind, yet you're giving to the basic weaknesses of like, oh, they're laughing and they're teasing me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you be beyond suffering, beyond the febrile emotion, when someone's mere teasing is affecting you, and you can't... you can't maintain your behavior?
[SPEAKER_01]: Timmy?
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's... precepts aren't... that's not all that you have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a lot more work... Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a fertile ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have all the fertile ground you want, if you don't have the actual well-cultivated seeds, and if you don't put the work in maintaining that soil, then they're not gonna grow.
[SPEAKER_01]: So being... Because you have to water it, you have to provide enough sun, you have to work around it, once you plant the seeds.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just leaving, just hoping for the soil to do its own, it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: To do the work, it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the soil.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can have 300 rules, 1000 rules, 5 rules, as many rules as you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter, because there's other work that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have the rules that cover the necessary basis, and those are basically what is known as eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or ten precepts, if you want to take it maybe a step further, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is derived from that basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot add more to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, yeah, having three thousand rules, it's not necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you've covered the basis of these eight precepts, if you don't do anything unwholesome on the account of the eight precepts, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have sufficient basis for complete freedom from suffering, from feelings and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what, what, what can you give like a... what's a basic, what's a basic set, precept, that anybody can follow?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: They can establish themselves in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't kill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't steal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't cheat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, preferably, or ideally, be a complete celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Live a completely celibate lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't... well, don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, don't drink and take drugs, in the sense of don't consume things that directly affect mindfulness and awareness and composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to... those are like the five basic ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they have to be basically taken seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm talking about somebody who still lives in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: For a monk, then you have the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the non-beautification, non-indulgence in sleep, and not eating at the wrong times.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in not just spend the whole day eating around and thinking about food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you wanna start kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Harnessing your mind, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Harnessing the outpours, the behaviors of your mind that are founded upon desire and non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you're setting up a fence, tying it down, pinning it down until it comes down.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the precepts are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in itself, they're not... it's not enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessary basis
[SPEAKER_01]: The container, but then the work needs to be done within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you fence the yard off for a wild horse, you need to start training it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the first... you can't start training it, inconceivable, when it can always run off into the mountains.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you fenced it off completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: You repaired any patches that he was escaping through.
[SPEAKER_01]: You brought it back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now he can't escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wait for it to calm down, because he will calm down sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's going to get tired running around in circles.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it's calm, then you start training it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you remove the fence and you haven't trained it, it's going to run off again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to keep the fence until it's fully trained, and when it's fully trained, then it doesn't matter if the fence stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically the definition of the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even as a layperson, the five precepts are at a certain degree of that... of that fence, which is... which is a good thing, because you are taming down the wild horse, which... what mind is, really, for most people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're taking a bit more control over your own behavior, over your own desires, over your own sort of impulses that usually you can't say no to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where growth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where development is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the first step.